Michael Ferral

Business Analyst

meferral@gmail.com

941-932-0074

linkedin.com/in/michaelferral/



github.com/meferral

Greater Nashville Area

SKILLS

- SQL (PostgreSQL)
- Python
- Tableau
- Power BI
- Excel (VLOOKUP, Pivot Tables, PowerPivot)
- Git/GitHub
- Zoom/Slack/Teams

EDUCATION & CREDENTIALS

NASHVILLE SOFTWARE SCHOOL

Data Analytics Bootcamp Graduate, Jan 2022

Nashville State Community College 2014 & 2017

Business, Technology, Economics & Accounting

Tallahassee Community College 2005-2007

ABOUT ME

I am an experienced leader who thrives in group settings as well as individual tasks.

My goal is to be a part of a progressive team in which I can help bring clarity to problems and provide solutions.

I am committed to sustainable practices both financially and ecologically.

DATA EXPERIENCE

Data Analyst Apprenticeship

NASHVILLE SOFTWARE SCHOOL | July 2021- January 2022

Six-month, intensive introduction to data analytics and business intelligence processes and tools. Learning includes communicating findings through presentations, storytelling, building reports/ creating dashboards. Tools learned: Excel, Python, SQL, Tableau, and PowerBI

PROIECTS

- Menu Cost Per Meal Dashboard- Capstone project automating Microsoft Products to run Python scripts that feed a dynamic real-time dashboard in PowerBI using data pulled from resources at Vanderbilt University- January 2022
- **Yelp Charlotte** Analyzed Yelp reviews in Charlotte NC bringing data together in PowerPivot and displaying dynamic figures mapping elements
- **Lahman Baseball Data Project-** Explored Lahaman's Baseball Database in an independent project using PostgreSQL to explore and answer prompts
- Basketball Power BI Dashboard- Explored PowerBI using Data from the 2014-2020 NBA Basketball Season

WORK EXPERIENCE

Vanderbilt University Campus Dining 5/2011- Present

Assistant Director May 2018-Present

- <u>Business Analytics</u> -Analyzed and communicated data trends related to labor and food costs. Worked with 10+ operational dining managers to evaluate trends and plans for business solutions. Compiled and communicated recommended changes to dining senior leadership team.
- <u>Food Management Software Implementation</u> Designed how software infrastructure would impact operations. Software included how operations forecasted, purchased, and displayed customer facing nutrition and menus.
- <u>Food Waste Software and Hardware Implementation</u>- Oversaw rollout of analytics software that tracked and analyzed waste trends
- <u>Forecasting, Process Improvement</u>- Took metrics from all systems and worked with analyst team to create and design operational dashboards
- <u>Contingency Planning</u>- Wrote executive summary for all Vanderbilt Campus Dining Residential Operations for many phases of COVID-19
- <u>Training & Development</u> Oversaw and created detailed trainings on all new systems rolled out so that processes could be repeatable
- Management and New Hire Orientation Program Design- was tapped in 2021 to be on a team that focused on development, onboarding, and training for all levels in Vanderbilt Campus Dining

General Manager July 2016- May 2018

Multi-Unit Manager June 2014- July 2016

Supervisor May 2011-June 2014

Steak n Shake Restaurants 8/2004-5/2011

Worked from an hourly position to a General Manager position with full store responsibility